http://youtu.be/Gagr_KyDYAA
http://youtu.be/Gagr_KyDYAA Tung Dinh _ VGU
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: The fun problem we're going to solve,
Chuyện tiếp theo ta làm là
is to build a robot that moves around in a box.
làm 1 robot đi vòng vòng trong hộp
And so, we're going to have walls around our robot
ta có cách cạnh của hộp
and we're going to place it inside.
và ta đặt con robot trong đây
So the problem we're going to solve today,
Vấn đề đặt ra hôm nay là
is what happens when the robot approaches a wall.
robot sẽ làm gì nếu đụng vào tường
So here's our stick figure robot and it is moving in this direction
Đây là robot, và nó đi theo hướng này
and when it hits the wall, we're going to make it rotate so it follows
khi đụng trúng tường, ta sẽ cho nó xoay và
along the wall.
đi dọc theo bức tường
Similarly, if the robot is traveling in the other direction,
Tương tự thì, nếu robot đi theo hướng khác
relative to the wall-- there's our robot and it is traveling in this direction,
đối với bức tường, hướng này đây
we're going to turn in the other direction and follow the wall that way.
ta sẽ cho nó xoay hướng khác, và đi dọc theo hướng này
In order to make this happen, the robot's going to need a way to move.
Để làm được, ta cần biết cách di chuyển của robot
So, we're going to place two stepper motors on the wheels, such
Ta sẽ đặt 2 motors bước cho bánh xe
that if the stepper motors are both turned in the same direction,
Nếu như 2 motors quay cùng hướng
it will move.
nó sẽ di chuyển
So, if the stepper motors are rotating, it will move.
So, if the stepper motors are rotating, it will move.
The second thing we're going to have to add, is sensors.
Cái thứ hai cần nữa là cảm biến
And so we're going to add two sensors, two bump sensors,
Ta sẽ đặt 2 cảm biến vào đây, cảm biến bơm
on the front of the robot, so I can tell if I've hit the wall.
ở phía trước của robot, nên ta có thể biết nó đụng tường chưa
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So, in the scenario at the top,
Theo đúng trình tự thì
you mean that when it hits the wall, it's
khi robot đụng tường
going to be the left sensor that's going to strike the wall first?
cảm biến trái sẽ chạm trước
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: OK, that's right.
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: OK, that's right.
So, if the left sensor hits first, we are then going to turn right.
Nếu cảm biến trái chạm trước, ta sẽ xoay phải
Conversely, if the right sensor hits first, we will then turn left.
Ngược lại, nếu cảm biến phải chạm trước, ta sẽ xoay trái
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So, how are we going
Ta sẽ giao tiếp
to interface this robot to our microcontroller?
robot với microcontroller thế nào?
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Let's begin with the battery.
Rồi, đầu tiên là pin
Because we have motors, we're not going to hook up the launchpad to the motors.
Vì ta dùng motors, ta sẽ không trực tiếp cấp nguồn motors bằng lauchpad
We'll use a battery.
Ta sẽ dùng pin
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: This will protect the launchpad
Điều này sẽ bảo vệ launchpad
when the motors draw too much current.
khi motors cần nhiều dòng
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Excellent, excellent.
Chính xác
Yes.
Yes.
In order to make the launchpad run, we'll use a regulator.
Để chạy launchpad, ta dùng điều chỉnh áp
And this will change our 8.4 volts, from the battery, into 5 volts.
đổi từ 8.4 V từ pin sang 5 V
And we'll tie that to Vbus to our launchpad.
Và nối vào Vbus ở launchpad
And the ground goes to ground.
ground nối vào ground
So, now the battery's running the launchpad.
Xong khoảng pin cấp nguồn lauchpad
To interface the motors, what I'm going to need is a motor driver.
Để giao tiếp với motors, ta sẽ dùng điều khiển motors
And so I'm going to use two L293s to drive the motor.
2 con L293 để điều khiển
And the stepper motors have two coils, A and B. We have two L293s
Motor bước có 2 cuộn dây, A và B. Ta có 2 L293s
because we have two stepper motors.
bởi ta dùng 2 motors bước
The left stepper motor and the right stepper motor.
1 bên trái, 1 bên phải
And we're going to connect, or control, the motors with a parallel output port.
Và ta sẽ điều khiển motors với các output ports song song
So, this is going to be PB7 through PB4.
Chúng là PB7 tới PB4
And this is the right motor.
và đối với motor phải
And we're going to have PB3 through PB0 four pins going to the left motor.
Ta dùng PB3 tới PB0
It's very important to watch the current.
Hiểu về dòng điện là rất quan trọng
The current across the motors is going to come from the battery connected
Dòng điện chạy qua motors là do từ pin
to my L293s, go across the coil, out the ground pins, and back to the battery.
nối tới L293, qua cuộng dây, tới chân ground, rồi quay về pin
And this current here, across these coils,
Dòng điện đây, chạy qua cuộn dây
does not pass through the launchpad or the microcontroller.
không chạy qua launchpad hay microcontroller
So, it goes directly from the battery, to the driver,
Nó chạy thẳng từ pin, sang bộ điề khiển
out the ground of the driver, and back to the battery.
tới chân ground của điều khiển, và ngược về pin
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: What about the inputs, Jon?
Inputs là gì thế Jon
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Yeah, we've got to connect up to inputs, don't we?
Đúng rồi, ta cũng phải nối inputs lại nữa
We've got two bump sensors, so we're going to tie them to PE0 and PE1.
Ta có ở đây 2 công tắc hành trình, nối chúng với PE0 và PE1
The left bump sensor is going to go to PE1
công tắc trái nối vào PE1
and the right bump sensor will go to PE0.
và phải nối vào PE0
These are going to be positive logic.
Chúng là logic dương
Again, if the right bumper hits, this will be a 1.
Nếu công tắc phải đụng, đây sẽ là 1
And if the left bumper
nếu cái trái đụng, đây sẽ là 1
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So, these are similar to the switches
Vậy thì, chúng cũng tương tự như công tắc thường
we saw, except they look more like bump sensors and not switches.
trừ việc nó nhìn giống như cảm biến
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Yeah, just like those.
Đúng rồi
Let's look at how the microcontroller controls the stepper motors.
Giờ ta sẽ tìm hiểu về cách microcontroller điều khiển motor bước
The stepper motors each have two coils, two windings.
Mỗi motor bước có 2 cuộn dây
One is called A and one is called B. There
A và B
are four pins, which output to the motors.
và 4 chân output của motor
If we output a 5, which is going to be a 0, 1, 0, 1,
Nếu ta output 5, sẽ là 0101
we see that current across the coil A will go up because there's a 1 here
Ta thấy dòng điện chạy qua cuộn dây A sẽ hướng lên, bởi đây là 1
and a 0 there.
và 0 ở đây
Similarly, the current will go up across the B coil.
Tương tự, dòng điện đi lên cuộn B
If we now change the output to a 6, what that will do,
Nếu ta đổi output thành 6, mọi chuyện sẽ là
is that will flip the current on the B coil.
nó sẽ đẩo chiều dòng điện ở cuộn B
The B coil is now going to have current which goes down.
Cuộn B bây giờ có dòng điện hướng xuống
The A current still goes up.
Ở cuộn A vấn hướng lên
This step is going to affect a change in the motor.
Bước này ảnh hưởng đến sự thay đổi trong motor
And so, if this is the motor here and we look at the angle
Ta quan sát góc
that this motor is at, this change from 5 to a 6
hiện tại của motor, thay đổi từ 5 sang 6
will cause the motor to rotate by an angle, which
sẽ làm cho motor quay 1 góc
is determined by the physics of the motor.
được xác định bằng tính vật lý của nó
In our case, this angle is going to be 1.8 degrees.
Trường hợp này là 1.8 độ
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So when I buy stepper motors,
Khi mua 1 motor bước
I choose my stepper motor based on what angle
Ta chọn dựa trên góc
it has to rotate in each step that I that I write to a stepper motor?
nó phải quay mỗi bước, mà ta viết lên?
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Yes.
Đúng rồi
This one has 200 steps per rotation But we're not done.
Cái này có 200 bước mỗi vòng, nhưng ta chưa viết hết
We have two more.
Còn 2 cái nữa
If we output a 10, what will happen is we're
Nếu ta output 10
going to rotate, or flip the current, on the other coil.
nó sẽ quay, đảo chiều dòng điện cuộn kia
And so now because the A coil sees a 1, 0, its current will go down.
Và bởi vì cuộng A là 10, dòng điện hướng xuống
The B coil is still 1, 0, so it is also going down.
Cuộn B vẫn là 10, hướng xuống
And the motor will rotate one more time of 1.8 degrees.
Và motor sẽ quay 1 bước 1.8 độ nữa
We've got one more and that is a 9, which is a 1, 0, 0, 1.
Ta còn 1 bước nữa là 9, 1001
You see each time we step it, we're flipping one of the currents in one
Bạn sẽ thấy rằng mỗi lần bước, ta sẽ đảo chiều
of the coils.
một trong 2 cuộn
Again, the A coil remained down-- 1, 0-- but the B coil flipped to be a 0, 1.
Nhắc lại, cuộn A vẫn đang hướng xuống, 10, nhưng cuộn B đã đảo thành 01
This pattern of 5, 6, 10, 9, is repeated over and over and over again.
Các bước 5 6 10 9 được lập lại
So, it goes 5, 6, 10, 9, 5, 6, 10, 9, repeated over and over again.
nó sẽ là 5 6 10 9 5 6 10 9 lập lại lập lại
Each time we step to a new value, it rotates 1.8 degrees.
Mỗi lần ta bước 1 giá trị mới, nó xoay 1.8 độ
So, it goes from a 5, 6, 10, 9, 5, 6, 10, 9.
từ 5 6 10 9 5 6 10 9
It rotates.
Nó xoay
So, in order to move both motors clockwise,
Để quay 2 motor cùng chiều kim đồng hồ
we're going to output the pattern 0x55, 0x66, 0xAA, 0x99, over and over again.
ta sẽ output dãy 0x55 0x66 0xAA 0x99 lần lượt lặp lại
The speed at which it rotates is going to be 1.8 degrees divided
Tốc độ quay sẽ là 1.8 độ
by the time in between outputs.
chia cho thời gian giữa outputs
So, in summary, with a stepper motor, we could
Tóm lại, với motor bước
control both the position of the shaft by stepping it 5,6, 10,9,
ta có thể điều khiển cả vị trí bằng 4 5 10 9
and we can also control the speed at which it runs,
và cũng có thể điều kheiern tốc độ xoay
by varying the time between steps.
bằng việc thay đổi thời gian giữa bước
So, let's build the finite state machine.
Tới máy trạng thái hữu hạn
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So, we can do a state transition graph,
Giờ ta viết sơ đồ máy trạng thái hữu hạn
but first we'll have to fill in all the elements of our finite state
nhưng đầu tiên, ta phải điền hết các điều kiện đã
machine, which is the set of inputs.
là chuỗi inputs
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Inputs.
Inputs
And we saw here, we have PE1 and PE0 are our inputs.
Ở đây ta có PE1 và PE0 là inputs
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: And we have our set of outputs.
Và chuỗi outputs
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: OK, we have outputs,
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: OK, we have outputs,
which we saw were PB7 through PB0.
ở đây là PB7 đến PB0
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: And then we have the set of states.
và chuỗi trạng thái
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Ah, states.
Đúng, trạng thái
We're going to have lots of states in our finite state machine.
Ta có nhiều trạng thái đây
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So, the state's will
Chúng sẽ
correspond to all the configurations we can find the robot in.
tương đương với từng trường hợp trong robot
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: So, we will use the states to specify what we know,
Vậy, ta sẽ dùng các trạng thái để xác định cái ta biết
what we believe to be true.
Cái ta biết là đúng
Two more.
2 cái nữa
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: And then we need the state transition graph,
Và rồi ta cũng cần đồ thị chuyển trạng thái nữa
which is going to tell us how we move from one state to another.
sẽ cho ta biết cách chuyển từ trạng thái này sang trạng thái khác
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: OK.
OK
So, for instance, if no switches are pressed, no bumpers are pressed,
Ví dụ, nếu không có công tắc nào nhấn
we are going to go in this direction and move.
ta sẽ đi theo hướng này
There's one more and that is output determination.
Thêm 1 cái nữa là xác định output
Output determination will cause something to happen.
nó sẽ làm di chuyển
So, we're going to use the outputs to change our world.
Tóm lại là ta dùng outputs để thay đổi
And in particular, we saw to move the robot forward
Rõ ràng hơn, thì ta thấy robot di chuyển thẳng tới
we're going to output a 0x55, 0x66, 0xAA, and 0x99.
ta sẽ đặt output là 0x55, 0x66, 0xAA và 0x99
That will rotate the motor forward.
Nó sẽ làm motor chạy thẳng
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: But what if I want to rotate the robot backwards?
Còn nếu ta muốn robot quay ngược lại thì sao?
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Oh, backwards.
Oh, ngược lại à?
To go backwards-- in other words, if both bumpers are hit--
Để đi ngược lại, nói cách khác, nếu cả hai công tắc bị nhấn
I can actually rotate the motor in the other direction.
ta có thể quay motor hướng khác
So, if I output a 0x99, 0xAA, 0x66, 0x55, because both sensors were hit,
Vậy nếu ta output 0x99 0xAA 0x66 0x55, bở cả 2 công tắc bị nhấn
both motors will rotate in the other direction
thì cả hai motor sẽ quay hướng khác
and the robot will go backwards.
và robot sẽ đi ngược
If I hit the right bumper, I want to turn left.
Nếu ta nhấn công tắc phải, nghĩ là ta quay trái
And we can turn left by rotating one of the steppers in one direction
Quay trái thì 1 motor quay hướng này
and the other in the other direction.
cái kia quay hướng khác
So, we see here, that one motor is going 5, 6, 10, 9,
Bạn thấy đấy, 1 motor sẽ là 5 6 10 9
while the other is going 5, 9, 10, 6, and that will turn the robot left.
cái kia sẽ là 5 9 10 6, thì robot sẽ quay trái
If I want to go right, in other words, if the other switches hit
Nếu ta mướn quay phải, nói cách khác, công tắc trái bị nhấn
and I want to turn right, I'll reverse it.
ta sẽ đảo thứ tự lại
In this way, one motor is going 5, 9, 10, 6, and the other
Nghĩa là, 1 motor là 5 9 10 6, và cái kia
is going 5, 6, 10, 9, and this will turn right.
là 5 6 10 9, robot sẽ quay phải
Again, the speed in which I rotate the motors
Nhắc lại, tốc độ quay motor
is dependent on the delta-t, the time between outputs,
phụ thuộc vào delta t, thời gian giữa các outputs
so I can choose to speed in degrees per second
Ta có thể chọn tốc độ là độ/s
by specifying the time between states.
bằng việc xác định thời gian giữa trạng thái
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So, one of the things
Vậy, một trong số đó
we want to make sure when we have a state transition graph
ta phải chắc chắn có đồ thị chuyển trạng thái
is we will indicate every label, every arrow has to be labeled,
ta cũng sẽ gán nhẵn từng đường mũi tên
which means that we have to account for all inputs in all states.
nghĩa là ta phải gán mọi inputs vào mọi trạng thái
So, Jon, will you complete the graph?
Vậy thì, Jon sẽ hoàn thiện hết đò thị cho bạn
DR. JONATHAN VALVANO: Of course.
OK
So, in this case, regardless of what the inputs going to be,
Trong trường hợp này, bất kể inputs là gì
I'm going to rotate a whole way around.
ta cũng sẽ quay nguyên một vòng
And over here, regardless of what this one is, I'm going to rotate around.
và ở đây, bất kể là gì, ta cũng quay một vòng
And so, you can see the decision will be made when it gets to the top state.
Bạn có thể thấy được output là gì khi nó đến trạng thái đầu
Similarly here, this one is 11, 11, 11.
Tương tự ở đây, 11 11 11
And this one is going to be a 01, 01.
và cái này sẽ là 01 01
And this is going to be 00, 01, 10, 00, 01, 10, 00, 01, 10.
Đây sẽ là 00 01 10 00 01 10 00 01 10
So, we specified for every state, all possible next states.
Vậy ta đã mặc định cho từng trạng thái có thể xảy ra rồi
So, each state has four next states.
Mỗi trạng thái sẽ có 4 trạng thái tiếp theo